today I've got a unique video for you
and this is going to cover what we can
learn about strength
training uh from using a wrench so most
of you have used a wrench before here
okay I've got my hip Thruster here and
let's say I'm trying to create torque
because torque is turning Force so
that's how the body moves as well you
move through rotation so the muscles
create muscle Force which creates joint
torque turns about a joint so the same
thing happens when you use a wrench so
if you can think about a wrench let's
say I was trying to use this wrench very
inefficiently I would probably push at
an angle really far down and just not
use much force so if I was doing this
you could see that this wouldn't produce
a lot of torque what are the three ways
in which I can improve torque using this
wrench the first way way is to improve
the angle at which I push upon the
wrench so if I'm pushing like this I
want to be perpendicular to this wrench
that way all of my force is effective
Force pushing straight against the
wrench so I would move my angle attack
to here now I'm
pushing at a perpendicular angle which
is going to increase torque okay the
second thing I can do is just push
harder and then the third thing is move
up and increase the lever arm so when I
do that now you can see I can turn the
bolt okay
so I'm going to review this three ways
to increase torque production using a
wrench the first way say on like this
the first way is to make sure I'm
pushing
perpendicularly the second way is to
increase the force and the Third Way is
just move out the lever all right levers
the lever is equally as important as the
force you're pushing pushing into the
wrench because you multiply the two
together to get torque okay so using the
same
concept now we can think of muscles
here
so here I've got a rudimentary drawing
of the gluteus maximus here and you can
see right here
that this is a mediumsized glute well
through strength training you can
hypertrophy muscles you can grow muscles
and then they can produce greater torque
but you actually improve torque
production through all three mechanisms
and let me show you how so let's say The
Joint Center is like right here the hip
joint Center all right I am going to do
I I I believe that some of my clients
have doubled their glute mass in six
months and I have some before and after
pictures with bikini competitors where
you can see they probably double their
muscle mass so what is does that do so
if you take a glute like this if you
look first of all the femur you know
comes down like
this so if you look at what what is the
angle of attack of these glute fibers on
the femur is that perpendicular no it's
not it's coming in at an angle like
that okay the glute muscle is what
creates the force that's what creates
the pushing uh or in actually the
pulling that's what creates the pulling
on the on the femur and so a larger
glute is going to increase force and
then the lever arm is just simply the
horizontal distance between the the
glute
fibers and here so that's the distance
so if you do strength train a strength
training regimen say you you lift
weights for 6 months and you increase
the size of your glutes by say
30% now the glute comes like this
all right and now you've got
more glute volume okay well what does
this
do what does this do to torque all right
you've got way more surface area here
we've got way more cross-sectional area
more muscle volume so you have more
contractile units to produce Force
you've also now look at this angle of
attack coming onto the femur now it's
coming in at a
more perpendicular angle so you've got
greater force a more efficient line of
force and now look at this moment arm
here look at the leverage this is called
a muscle moment arm but it's it's
indicative of its leverage so all of the
fibers in the deep down in the center
are more of the type one fibers on the
outside are more of the type two fibers
and if
torque
equals force time perpendicular distance
then you can see your but uh it's it's
the effective Force right it's the um
perpendicular force times the the
perpendicular distance so you're going
to get greater
force more efficient Force which is
going to increase this even more and
you're going to increase the moment arm
so what we showed in my recent manual
that I put out the biomechanics of the
squat and deadlift manual in my 2x4
product we showed that a 30% increase in
glute volume actually led to a 50%
increase in torque production so that
just goes to show you that you you gain
strength a bigger muscle can create
greater torque production and it's very
valuable for all all sorts of Endeavors
whether it's a Athletics or strength or
um you know sprinting or things like
that jumping greater glute mass is going
to equal greater hip extension torque
thanks for watching the video